<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?asciidoc-toc maxdepth="2"?>
<?asciidoc-numbered?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:lang="en">
<info>
<title>Introduction</title>
<date>2021-05-21</date>
</info>
<chapter xml:id="_introduction">
<title>Introduction</title>
<simpara>QALIPSIS is an open-source, enterprise-grade load and performance-testing tool especially designed for distributed systems.</simpara>
<simpara>It can also run on standalone systems enabling users get the best from both worlds – simplicity and scalability.</simpara>
<simpara>Boasting a high degree of flexibility, QALIPSIS allows users to configure action paces and repetitions for seamless load-test campaigns.</simpara>
<simpara>To achieve this, QALIPSIS brings different core concepts together:</simpara>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>Scenarios: QALIPSIS’ scenarios are the single largest components a developer has to put in place in order to run a load test. They contain the steps with a detailed description of all the operations to accomplish, their dependencies, as well as the assertions to ensure everything performs as expected.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Steps: Steps are the central components for working with QALIPSIS and can be developed in Kotlin, Groovy or Java, using either JUnit-like classes or the fluent API. Steps, to a large degree, are dependent on data sources, results of other steps or assertions to execute or use their data.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Assertions: Assertions make it easy to perform cross-checks of data and durations from different sources. Validating data persistence, message exchanges or requests to remote systems has never been so easy. Durations can also be set and tested in order to verify the overall responsiveness of the system.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Minions: QALIPSIS can simulate website users, IoT devices or other systems. They are handled by a minion, which performs a complete scenario. You can even create millions of minions. Unlike other load-testing tools, due to the very low memory footprint, you can perform these tasks on a standard computer.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Head: QALIPSIS doesn’t only test distributed systems, but also runs as one. When a user needs to perform load tests at scale, or from different geographical locations, the user needs only to set up a cluster. The head component is only responsible for orchestration and reporting.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Factories: In an QALIPSIS cluster, the factories are the distributed components which host the minions to execute the load tests and assertions. Testers can even change the number of factories on-the-fly so as to optimize the load and cost of the testing infrastructure.</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<simpara>Now you can imagine all the incredible things you can achieve with QALIPSIS, create your first scenario and verify your sofware is working as you expect!</simpara>
</chapter>
</book>