<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?asciidoc-toc?>
<?asciidoc-numbered?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:lang="en">
<info>
<title>Introduction</title>
<date>2021-12-01</date>
</info>
<section xml:id="_introduction" role="data-line-1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<simpara role="data-line-3">QALIPSIS is an open-source, enterprise-grade load and performance-testing tool especially designed for distributed systems.</simpara>
<simpara role="data-line-5">QALIPSIS is a step above other load test applications that merely evaluate your system internally.</simpara>
<itemizedlist role="data-line-7">
<listitem role="data-line-7">
<simpara>QALIPSIS is developer-centric with a low learning curve that makes it easy to use and extremeley efficient.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem role="data-line-9">
<simpara>QALIPSIS is developed in Kotlin to gain the benefits of the Java ecosystem and provide seamless system performance.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem role="data-line-11">
<simpara>QALIPSIS&#8217;s open source version is completely free of charge.
(Plugins, the cloud-based application, and other premium extensions are not included in the open source vesion.)</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem role="data-line-14">
<simpara>QALIPSIS is designed to test the performance of distributed and monolith systems.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem role="data-line-16">
<simpara>QALIPSIS collects data from operating systems, databases and monitoring tools.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem role="data-line-18">
<simpara>QALIPSIS cross-checks system metrics and performs data verification to ensure that your systems is performing as expected.</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<section xml:id="_features" role="data-line-21">
<title>Features</title>
<section xml:id="_user_friendly_interface" role="data-line-23">
<title>User-friendly Interface</title>
<simpara role="data-line-25">The QALIPSIS Graphical User Interface (GUI) allows users to drive straightforward test runs: start and stop, change the load distribution and increase or decrease the number of simulated users.</simpara>
</section>
<section xml:id="_automation_friendly_performance_verification" role="data-line-28">
<title>Automation Friendly Performance Verification</title>
<simpara role="data-line-29">Using the CLI or the Gradle plugin, you can automatically and repeatedly verify the condition and performance of your system.</simpara>
</section>
<section xml:id="_developer_friendly_plug_ins" role="data-line-31">
<title>Developer Friendly Plug-ins</title>
<simpara role="data-line-33">Downloading a ready-to-use project for your IDE is made easier on QALIPSIS, consequently integrating with popular DevOps tools to test your software and track the impact of recent changes.</simpara>
</section>
<section xml:id="_aggregated_assertions" role="data-line-35">
<title>Aggregated Assertions</title>
<simpara role="data-line-36">Aggregated assertions allow you to verify the overall results on a scenario. You can define thresholds to make a test succeed or fail and immediately get insights about the performance and consistency of your tested system.</simpara>
<simpara role="data-line-38">Testing, Performance, and Geographical Distribution</simpara>
<itemizedlist role="data-line-40">
<listitem role="data-line-40">
<simpara>QALIPSIS can test distributed systems.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem role="data-line-41">
<simpara>QALIPSIS can perform as a distributed system.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem role="data-line-42">
<simpara>QALIPSIS can simulate load from several geographic locations to run comparisons based on location.</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>
<section xml:id="_live_results" role="data-line-44">
<title>Live Results</title>
<simpara role="data-line-46">QALIPSIS events and meters provide extended details of load-test operations, providing users with various options for accessing the results. The results visualizations and dashboards, with details of each test-case execution, provide valuable insight for identifying the bottlenecks in your applications and uncovering the components and conditions of failures.</simpara>
</section>
<section xml:id="_concurrent_load_simulations" role="data-line-48">
<title>Concurrent Load Simulations</title>
<simpara role="data-line-50">QALIPSIS simulates the load from thousands to millions of users (e.g., website visitors, connected IoT devices, etc) and cross-verifies successive values from different sources including requests, responses, infrastructure metrics, messaging platforms and databases.</simpara>
</section>
<section xml:id="_operating_system_independent" role="data-line-53">
<title>Operating System Independent</title>
<simpara role="data-line-54">QALIPSIS load and performance testing can be performed from any operating system supporting Java with the same impressive results.</simpara>
</section>
</section>
<section xml:id="_benefits" role="data-line-57">
<title>Benefits</title>
<simpara role="data-line-59">QALIPSIS was designed with distributed systems and current developer practices in mind. It provides a testing framework to allow developers to work in a real-world environment, writing and running load tests without a steep learning curve.</simpara>
<section xml:id="_for_developers" role="data-line-61">
<title>For Developers</title>
<simpara role="data-line-62">QALIPSIS empowers developers to:</simpara>
<itemizedlist role="data-line-64">
<listitem role="data-line-64">
<simpara>Choose their own testing tools and preferred programming language for writing load-test scenarios.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem role="data-line-66">
<simpara>Cross-verify data from different sources: bring responses to requests, infrastructure metrics, middleware events and database records in the same port to compare them and verify that they match your expectations.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem role="data-line-68">
<simpara>Unlock the full power of the Java ecosystem by making use of any library, protocol or system.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem role="data-line-70">
<simpara>Reuse pieces of their own software to faster develop scenarios.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem role="data-line-71">
<simpara>Simulate users, third-party software and IoT devices.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem role="data-line-72">
<simpara>Simulate real-user and device behavior to make load tests more relevant.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem role="data-line-73">
<simpara>Generate detailed and relevant results by using distributed tracing markers to follow the complete execution workflow from end to end.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem role="data-line-74">
<simpara>Customize reports and dashboards.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem role="data-line-75">
<simpara>Perform tests on development machines, containers and virtual machines with excellent results.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem role="data-line-76">
<simpara>Integrate their standard DevOps workflow for performance testing before the deployment of health checks on production environments.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem role="data-line-78">
<simpara>Create a scenario in just a few minutes by enabling utilization of any Java library of choice (such as JUnit, Hamcrest, AssertJ) or pieces of software or proprietary libraries.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem role="data-line-80">
<simpara>Test non-http technologies using numerous plug-ins, such as databases and messaging platforms.</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>
<section xml:id="_for_it_operations_teams" role="data-line-82">
<title>For IT Operations Teams</title>
<simpara role="data-line-83">QALIPSIS provides IT Operations teams solutions to:</simpara>
<itemizedlist role="data-line-85">
<listitem role="data-line-85">
<simpara>Monitor how deployments and other IT operations can affect the availability and overall performance of the system.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem role="data-line-86">
<simpara>Expose bottlenecks and find correlations between load and resource consumption by unifying the verification of load-test and infrastructure metrics.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem role="data-line-87">
<simpara>Identify issues before users and customers do by verifying the size and configuration of the system&#8217;s infrastructure.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem role="data-line-88">
<simpara>Examine how the system performs during normal and peak loads by running load tests from different geographic locations at varying times.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem role="data-line-89">
<simpara>Generate exceptional results on virtual engines, containers and conventional development machines.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem role="data-line-90">
<simpara>Allow for implementation and integration of verifications in their standard DevOps workflow.</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>
</section>
<section xml:id="_core_concepts" role="data-line-94">
<title>Core Concepts</title>
<simpara role="data-line-95">Boasting a high degree of flexibility, QALIPSIS allows users to configure and execute seamless campaigns that test specific features of their system.</simpara>
<simpara role="data-line-97">To achieve this, QALIPSIS brings the following core concepts together:</simpara>
<itemizedlist role="data-line-99">
<listitem role="data-line-99">
<simpara>Scenarios - The single largest components of a QALIPSIS load test.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem role="data-line-101">
<simpara>Steps - The central atomic components within each scenario.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem role="data-line-103">
<simpara>Assertions - Steps that perform cross-checks of data, execution states and durations from different sources.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem role="data-line-105">
<simpara>Minions - Virtual actors simulating website users, IoT devices, or other systems that interact with the test system to inject load and verify behavior performance.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem role="data-line-107">
<simpara>Head - The component of a cluster that is responsible for orchestration and reporting.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem role="data-line-109">
<simpara>Factories - The distributed components of a cluster which host the minions to execute the load tests and assertions.</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<simpara role="data-line-111">These concepts are discussed in detail in the Qalipsis Core Concepts Section. Add a link!!!!</simpara>
<simpara role="data-line-113">Once you have a minimal understanding of the core concepts, you will be ready to create a QALIPSIS "Hello World" scenario to  verify that your software is performing as expected.</simpara>
</section>
</section>
</article>